hello and welcome i'm your code monkey
and here's a really awesome project that
i made it's a turn-based strategy action
game very much inspired by the likes of
xcom and so it only took me about 30
hours to build this project and i'm
quite happy with the final result it's
got all of the mechanics you expect
there's turn-based combat and movement
it has line of sight both full and half
cover an overwatch mechanic and of
course a hit percentage for those
awesome 99 misses in this video let's
check out how i made it starting from
scratch until the final polished game
also stick around to the end where i
have a very exciting announcement to
share if you prefer a more guided path
with step-by-step lectures then check
out my complete courses learn how to
make a builder defender game using c
sharp just like i make my own steam
games or learn how to make games
internally using visual scripting or
learn all about unity with the ultimate
overview course which contains over 13
lectures each covering a different tool
or feature of the engine to help you
make better games faster i'm always
available in the courses q a section
answering your questions every single
day so check out all the courses with
the link in the description so i started
off like i usually start these projects
thinking on paper and writing down some
basic design this is obviously inspired
by xcom so i inspected the game to see
what were the crucial features and i
also took some time to think about how i
would structure the code for example i
realized that everything in the game is
really an action shooting is an action
abilities are an action and even just
simple movement is also an action so i
thought quite a bit on what is the best
way to implement that logic in the code
using a nice common interface then i
open a new project and just start
working on it like i said it's all about
action so i start off implementing a
basic movement action setting up the
main unit class in the interface and
making a move action that implements it
with that the character was just moving
in a straight line also for the visuals
over here i'm using the super useful
cinti studios prototype pack
i think this one was free during a bunch
of giveaways so chances are you already
have it these are pretty nice simple
assets then of course since the game is
grid based i once again reused my super
useful grid system if you are new to the
channel check out the home playlist this
class and this playlist is one of the
best examples of the power writing clean
reusable code
i originally made it over three years
ago and now it just took me five minutes
to implement a working grid with that
then i added some grid movement so
instead of having the unit move directly
to the path now it goes in a grid path
one great position at a time however at
this point still note pathfinding so it
just moves all horizontally and then
home vertically up next i want to be
able to move to where i clicked so i
implement the simple mouse click and
mouse position once again we're using a
super awesome class i made in a previous
video it gets me the mouse position in
the world then using that i can tell the
unit where to move then with the grid
position object i had the field for the
unit and some logic to know where that
unit was so just by looking at the grid
itself i can know exactly what unit is
occupying what position then for the
installation once again i spend quite
some time thinking about design thinking
about what would be the best way to
implement this and i came up with a
simple class to manage the current
active unit and action
since i know which unit is on which grid
position it's actually very easy to
handle selection
i just need to check the grid position
under the mouse and check if there's a
unit on it and if so select it then just
add a simple visual to know which one is
selected again all while writing some
nice clean code so the visual is
completely separated from the system
then once again some more thinking time
now this time thinking about how to best
implement multiple actions i realized
that a lot of them would have quite a
lot of things in common like what unit
that action belongs to and a combat they
store on action complete so with that i
made a base class with all of that
common logic then i started implementing
multiple actions starting with a simple
spin action just spinning the character
in place this action obviously makes no
sense in the final game but over here
it's very simple and very visual so it's
great to make sure that the whole system
works great with any number of actions
of any type and at this point the game
was already starting to take shape
despite the fact that it was just two
hours of development so this really
showcases three things one it's the
power of writing clean reasonable code i
first made the grid system three years
ago and now it just took me five minutes
to reuse it and also the mouse position
i also made that video about two years
ago and here i just reused the same
class
another thing this showcase is the power
of pre-production since i dedicated
quite a few days to preparing an offline
for what i want to build when i actually
started building it i already had a
pretty nice idea of exactly what i
needed to build so what systems i needed
to make and how they would interact with
one another and finally this showcased
the power of experience really if i had
tried to make this game 10 years ago
when i was just starting with unity back
then it would have taken me weeks or
maybe a month to get to this point but
thanks to all of the experience i
already have i really managed to build
this in just under two hours so those
are three really nice takeaways from
just the beginning of this project okay
so everything was already looking pretty
good next up was adding one very crucial
thing to this game adding action points
and a turn system i want to be able to
spend action points doing some actions
then end the turn and have the action
points reset
for the character visual elements i use
a world space canvas ui it's super
useful i made a video on that each unit
has a nice overlay showing the action
points after that i implemented health
once again reusing my health system from
the very first video on this channel
very simple to add just add the visual
to the character overlay and made a
simple shoot action so just by clicking
on another unit it deals damage super
simple also at this point you could spam
click and take actions at the same time
as other actions so this can really
cause a lot of bugs so i just added a
simple turn blocker basically it blocks
any actions while the current one is
running very simple and fixes tons of
issues after that i just added some
animations just to look a bit better so
just some simple moving and shooting
animations then for the actions instead
of debug keys i made a proper ui just
some simple buttons and when selected
they enable a specific action on the
current selected unit and for selecting
units it's still the same so while in
move action if you click on top of
another unit then instead of moving
there it just selects that unit after
that was something very important having
a grid visual here i went with a super
simple approach just spawning a simple
prefab on every single grid position now
this one is not the most performant
approach but it works pretty well in
this case
if i wanted maximum performance then i
would implement a single mesh just like
it did in the heat map video or even the
2d xcom video but for this quick demo
this really works more than good enough
with the grid visual done i then
expanded each action to return a list of
all of the valid grid positions so you
can no longer move an infinite amount or
move just 0 units also you cannot shoot
an infinite distance so it needs to be
within a certain range for the action to
be valid thanks to how all of the code
is set up in a nice clean way it's super
simple to add unique rules for each
action then i added something extremely
important some simple pathfinding
actually reuse the exact same script
that i made in the pathfinding video
that video teaches you how the a star
pathfinding algorithm works so check it
out if you want to understand it the
only downside with the exact class made
in that video is that it's not really
intended to be performant but again in
this case since this is a turn-based
shooter maximum performance isn't really
a requirement related to the pathfinding
was obviously making some paths either
walkable or unwalkable so for that i
just added a collateral for each solid
object that i want to block path and i
play stack and ladder in a specific
layer then right when the game starts
the pathfinding is created and goes
through every single grid position and
there's a raycast to see if there's any
walker there if so the grid position
becomes unworkable and if not then it's
normal so some pretty simple logic and
with that pathfinding was fully working
up next for a bit of fun i added a
ragdoll to the units when they die it's
really simple it's using unity's
built-in breakdown wizard which is
actually one of the tools that i cover
in my ultimate unity overview course
it's pretty easy to use a tool and make
any character turn into a ragdoll so now
when the inside they fall to the ground
in a nice satisfying way also at this
point there was no concept of enemy or
friendly so i just quickly added that
just a simple bowling variable so either
unit is friendly or an enemy after that
i implemented some camera movement super
simple for this i use send machine which
makes camera handling extremely easy
just made the virtual camera follow a
target object then with a simple script
just move that object rotated and
applied some zoom for another quick
visual improvement i enabled screen
space ambient occlusion this one is a
subtle effect but it looks pretty great
it's also somewhat hidden but i made a
video on how to enable it if you don't
know about it then it was finally time
to tackle one of the more complex tasks
start working on the enemy ai first
start off with the easiest part just
making the enemy take a turn so it just
makes sure that it's the player's turn
and then when the player ends their turn
the enemy takes theirs with that basic
logic working then it was time to make
the enemy take actions again starting
simple just testing the logic to make it
take an action so all it does is take a
spin action while it has action points
and after all the enemies spend their
action points then the enemy ends their
turn and goes back to the player
without working then it was time to make
some proper ai
i spent quite some time thinking about
this naturally ai is a massive topic you
could spend hours weeks or even years
just working on ai for this quick demo i
wanted something functional but as
simple as possible so the rules that i
implemented were pretty simple if you
can shoot a player character then shoot
if not move somewhere and to test where
to move assign some points depending on
the number of targets in range of that
new position
so basically it tries to move to where
it can shoot at least one player unit
and then if there's something in range
then just shoot them
also made them prioritize weaker units
so if there's a unit with half health
and one with full health then it targets
the weakest this is also the best tactic
when actually playing xcom you want to
remove as many enemy units as possible
okay so with that very basic ai done
then i worked on a fun task making an
action camera once again pretty easy
thanks to using cinemachine just made
another virtual camera then through code
when someone takes an action it
positions the camera right behind the
shooter looking at the target
and when the action is done it simply
disables the virtual camera and it goes
back to the regular virtual camera up
next it was time to work on another
crucial system making the cover system
for defining cover it was pretty easy
every object that's already blocking
pathfinding meaning every solid object
for all of those i just added another
script which defines if that object
works as half or full cover it's really
similar to how the pathfinding works
just goes through every single grid
position to check the cover state
and simply sets that state on that grid
position so populating the world with
cover points is super easy for the cover
animation i just went into miximo and
downloaded a free crouch idling mission
mixamo is an awesome website where you
can download free animations that work
on any project i made a video on that
home process then i decided to continue
working on the game during a live stream
thank you all for joining me first task
on stream was a simple one just make a
cover icon so it's just an image it
listens to the events when the unit
changes great position and just updates
the icon super simple then i also
quickly made some high crates just took
out the normal crates stretch them out
change the cover script value to say
these are now phone cover with that done
i then decided to build another action a
throw grenade action creating the action
itself was pretty easy thanks to how the
code is set up in a nice clean way i
just need to make an action script that
implements the interface and write down
the throw grenade code for throwing it
just spawns a visual prefab and moves it
over time since the player can throw at
various distances then the grenade
movement couldn't be a static animation
it had to be driven by code for the
horizontal movement i made it as normal
but for the vertical movement i went
with the approach of using an
interesting animation curve this one is
a really awesome unity feature that has
tons of use cases don't be fooled by the
name this can be used for anything not
just animations you can place the points
and draw the curve exactly as you want
it so in my case i use the animation
curve to define the y-axis so the
grenade moves and then when it lands i
just spawn some nice and simple
particles and finally for dealing damage
i just did a physics overlap sphere to
find all the objects in range find all
of the unit objects and call the deal
damage function then i also wanted to
add a nice destruction to the cover
objects for that i used the method that
i covered in a previous video just using
pro builder to slice the crate into
multiple pieces then i just spawn the
prefab when the crate is destroyed and
apply some force to make all the parts
go fine as you can see it's really easy
to add some destruction in your games
and looks really awesome that was the
end of the live stream thank you all for
joining me back to working on it by
myself i started working on the fog of
war system units should not be able to
see all over the map if an enemy is
behind the wall it should be invisible
handling that logic was very similar to
what i covered in the line of sight
field of view videos i just start from
each unit position then i do some math
to get all of the directions around the
unit and test the grid positions at
various distance points if the grid
position has a full cover object then
the unit cannot see further it's some
pretty simple logic and it works great
just need to then connect it to the
enemy logic just add some simple code to
hide the visual so the enemy still works
as normal just invisible and that's
pretty much it and it works next was
adding a crucial mechanic for this game
type calculating a hit percentage now
this one is pretty easy to add you can
make it as complex as you want in the
math but really i just kept it simple
basically just took into account the
distance to the target also whether the
target was in cover or not then with
that i also had an accuracy film to each
unit just to add a tiny bit of
randomness if you had a more persistent
game like xcom with the overwhelm then
you could load your soldier accuracy
stats for this simple prototype i'm
happy with the simple math that i have
here it adds a degree of randomness to
your hits but it can also be managed by
the player simply playing better by
getting into cover and approaching the
enemies before firing up next was a fun
mechanic adding an overwatch this one is
also quite simple thanks to how
everything is set up for making the
action since all the code is set up in a
nice clean way it was pretty easy to add
another action then for the logic
basically i just need to know what is
the overwatch range and since i already
have events when every unit changes with
position i just listen to that and see
if the enemy unit entered within the
overwatch range and if so just shoot
them using the same cal hit percent with
a bit of a penalty so that's really it
it works great and this ability was
super easy to make with that all of the
mechanics were pretty much done so i
just quickly set up a nice level placing
down walls crates enemies and so on and
with that over here is the final result
alright so here i am on turn one
i've got my team right here and over
here is a bunch of enemies there is a
fog war system so i can't see any more
enemies around this area
then down here i can select which action
i want to take and by clicking i can
select which unit and by default the
move action shows me everywhere that i
can move and of course there's the walls
with phone cover and he creates some
with phone cover some with half cover
so i'm going to move my unit over there
and there you go he runs and now he's
got full cover
and i can go into the shoot action and
try to hit any of these and of course
they've got a certain hit percentage
that one is on phone cover so the hit
percentage is really low then this one
is closer than this one so let's try
hitting this one 78 percent chance so
click there you go the nice camera zoom
in the nice shot and in this case it
actually missed
so now this one is out of action point
so let's select another one
move them into a bit of cover
in this case maybe throw a grenade just
throw and boom deals nice aoe damage
and for this one just without moving
just shoot down and try to hit if there
you go nice hit another one and if there
you go another nice hit and as soon as
the enemy dies there goes a really nice
ride off
okay so i'm out of action points and now
it's time to let the enemy take their
turn
the enemy ai is currently running
and all of the various enemies are
taking their action that one decides to
take a shot and there you go once two
shots then another one wins a shot there
goes one of my units and another one
getting hit
yep as soon as the enemy takes all their
turns now it's my turn again so once
again i can move i can attack i can
throw some grenades and so on
the game also has some nice
destructibility so if i fire a grenade
over there and there's a crate just fire
the grenade and boom there you go it
also blows up the box
and the final skill is the overwatch so
i just enable overwatch and my turn
and there's the enemy starts to move and
as soon as he gets within range he gets
a nice shot alright so that's the
minigame pretty awesome now here's the
exciting announcement that i mentioned
in the beginning the reason why i made
this quick pro tap is because this is
going to be my next complete course this
is a pretty fun genre i think a lot of
people would like to learn how to make
this specific type of game something
turn-based strategy with actions combat
abilities movement and so on and
personally i also really like it so it's
perfect for my next complete
step-by-step course it's going to be in
the same format as my other courses so
starting commonly from scratch and going
step by step until the final polish game
so if that's something you're interested
in there's a link description where you
can sign up and i'll let you know when
it's out as for timing it's always very
tricky to know exactly but i already
have this prototype and the outline and
a lot of things already done so
hopefully within the next one to two
months so if you're interested in that
course sign up on the website thank you
for watching and i'll see you next time
[Music]
you